<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Zebra Antelope - Getting Started</title>
		<author email="bgidley@berlios.de">Ben Gidley</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Introduction">
			<p>Antelope is a sample application using the Zebra workflow 
				engine.</p>
			<p>It is based on </p>
			<ul>
				<li>Turbine 2.4-M1-Dev</li>
				<li>Hibernate</li>
				<li>Zebra</li>
			</ul>
			<p>This application is designed to be used in a development 
				environment using Eclipse and Maven - it is possible to run and 
				use this without these but no instructions are provided.</p>
		</section>
		<section name="To develop and run the sample">
			<p>You will need</p>
			<ul>
				<li>A copy of Antelope either cvs or zip</li>
				<li>Maven 1.0.2 <a 
					href="http://maven.apache.org/">http://maven.apache.org/</a></li>
				<li>Java SDK 1.4.2 <a 
					href="http://java.sun.com">http://java.sun.com</a></li>
				<li>Eclipse 3<a 
					href="http://www.eclipse.org">http://www.eclipse.org</a></li>
				<li>Tomcat 4.1.x or 5 <a 
					href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat</a></li>
				<li>Sysdeo Tomcat Plugin for eclipse <a 
					href="http://www.sysdeo.com/eclipse/tomcatPlugin.html">http://www.sysdeo.com/eclipse/tomcatPlugin.html</a></li>
			</ul>
			<p> You may want the following eclipse plugins - as they make 
				development easier</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Veloclipse 				http://propsorter.sourceforge.net/veloeclipse</li>
				<li>XMLBuddy for eclipse http://xmlbuddy.com/</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section name="Getting Antelope">
			<subsection name="CVS">
				<p>The best way to get Antelope it directly from CVS within 
					Eclipse. This way you can get updates easily and you don't 
					have to wait for the developers to make a new zip file.</p>
				<ul>
					<li>In eclipse go to the CVS Perspective.</li>
					<li>Add a repository with 
						<ul> 
							<li>Server - cvs.zebra.berlios.de</li> 
							<li>username anonymous</li> 
							<li>type pserver</li> 
							<li>path /cvsroot/zebra</li>
						</ul> 
					</li>
					<li>Expand that repository to 
						HEAD\zebra\src\java\antelope</li>
					<li>Right click and check out as a project</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Zip">
				<p>You can download a <a 
					href="https://developer.berlios.de/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2683">zip</a> 
					of a recent antelope. It is recommend to use CVS rather than this as it make upgrading simpler</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="To use">
			<p>The Headline steps for each item <strong>see below</strong> for details</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Install software</li>
				<li>Run maven in the antelope folder</li>
				<li>Open the antelope project</li>
				<li>Start tomcat</li>
			</ol>
			<p>It should work!</p>
			<p>any problems please post to the Zebra Users mailing list <a 
				href="http://developer.berlios.de/mail/?group_id=2683">http://developer.berlios.de/mail/?group_id=2683</a></p>
			<subsection name="Install software">
				<p>Maven should be installed using the installer available from 
					apache. If you are on unix unzip it, and put maven in the 
					path. You will need to have Java set up in the path for it 
					to work</p>
				<p>Once maven is installed you will need to upgrade your
					maven Eclipse plugin by running the following command</p>
					<p>
						<code>maven plugin:download -DgroupId=maven -DartifactId=maven-eclipse-plugin -Dversion=1.8</code>
					</p>
					
				<p>You need to install a Java SDK (not just JRE) Sun have 
					instructions on this.</p>
				<p>Eclipse comes as a zip file, simply get the right zip for 
					your platform and unzip it. There will be an 'eclipse' 
					executable in the eclipse folder of the zip.</p>
				<p>Install Tomcat using the installer.</p>
				<p>Install the sysdeo tomcat plugin by copying it to the 
					eclipse/plugins folder and restarting eclipse. Once 
					installed in Window Preferences you must tell eclipse where 
					you installed tomcat. There is a bug in eclipse M8 that 
					preferences do not always apply in the tomcat plugin unless 
					you click both the apply and ok buttons.</p>
				<p>Right click on one of the menus and choose customise 
					perspective. On the commands tab enable the tomcat menus. 
					(You will need to do this for each Eclipse perspective you 
					use)</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name = "Run maven in the antelope folder">
				<p>Maven is used to build the project. This first hurdle we 
					have to cross is to put non redistributable jars in the local
					maven repository.</p>
				<p>Due to licensing issues (they are not 
					redistributable on their own) they are not on the central 
					maven sites. Instead you should copy them from the antelope 
					folder to the maven repository</p>
				<p>Your local maven repository will have been created at 
					HOME_DIRECTORY/.maven/repository</p>
				<p>On Windows XP you home directory will be c:\Documents and 
					Settings\USERNAME</p>
				<p>On Linux it will be /home/USERNAME</p>
				<p>Copy the contents of ANTELOPE/MavenRepo to your local maven 
					repo run maven eclipse again. It should succeed.</p>
				<p>It is recommended to put maven in your path - as it makes it 
					easier to use.</p>
				<p>Change to the folder antelope is in and run</p>
				<p>
					<code>maven antelope:start-hsql</code>
				</p>
				<p>This will start the simple hsql database leave this running. 
					You will need to start this (or change to a proper database)
					to run the application.</p>
				<p>You will see various Maven related messages and it will 
					download the jars Antelope needs</p>
				<p>Next we will run the build goal. This builds the code,
					creates the database tables and populates them with some
					administration data to get us started.</p>
				<p>
					<code>maven antelope:setup</code>
				</p>
				<p>You need to rerun this goal if you want to change the database
					structure.</p>
				<p>In Eclipse Windows -> Preferences -> Java -> Build Path 
					->Classpath Variables Add a variable called MAVEN_REPO 
					pointing to the folder holding your local maven 
					repository</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name = "Open the antelope project">
				<p>In eclipse use File -> Import to open the project you have 
					downloaded.</p>
				<p>It should build immediately without any errors.</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name = "Start tomcat">
				<p>Right click the project name and verify you have Tomcat Project
					menu option.  If you don't, then click properties, and choose
					Tomcat option.  Click "Is a Tomcat Project" and set the context to
					"/antelope".  Then mark can update server.xml.  Lastly, set the 
					webapp root to "/src/webapp"</p>
				<p>Next we need to register the project with Tomcat by right 
					clicking on the project name choosing Tomcat Project and 
					clicking on Update Context in server.xml</p>
				
				<p>From the Tomcat menu choose start. It should start.</p>
				<p>Go to http://localhost:TOMCATPORT/antelope Use antelope and 
					test as the username/password.</p>
				<p>Now have a look round. There are series of How does this work pages
					and sample pages. On most pages the links at the bottom of the page will 
					let you view the source code for the page.</p>
				<p>
					Note: These directions assume you already have Tomcat installed and the
					Sysdeo Tomcat plugin referencing the installation.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name = "Troubleshooting">
			<p>Q: Why does eclipse copy some files to a network drive and store 
				some locally in Windows XP</p>
			<p>A: This is because you have pinned the eclipse.exe to the start 
				menu. Doing this sets the working folder as your home drive. 
				Instead remove the eclipse.exe from the start menu. Create a 
				shortcut to it and pin the shortcut to the start menu.</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Known Issues">
			<p>See <a 
				href="http://developer.berlios.de/bugs/?group_id=2683">Bugs</a> 
				for known issues with antelope</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Where to go next">
			<p>Look at the application - specifically the how does this work section</p>
			<p>See the <a href="building.html">building guide</a> for how to compile it once you have a copy</p>
			
		</section>
	</body>
</document>