<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Antelope</title>
		<author email="bgidley@berlios.de">Ben Gidley</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="What is this?">
			<p> This is the page for the Antelope Sample application.</p>
			<p>Antelope aims to demonstrate how to us Zebra with Turbine 2.4 
				and Hibernate</p>
			<p>The original authors of zebra believe this to be an example of 
				good practice - obviously you are free to make up your mind</p>
			<p>The sample is designed to highligh the simplicity of building 
				flows and forms. We have not cut any corners or left out bits 
				we would normally use.</p>
			<p>To get started using this application please see <a 
				href="GettingStarted.html">Getting Started</a> </p>
			<subsection name="Hows does this all work">
				<p>As part of Antelope there are pages in the application 
					explaining how it all works. </p>
				<p>Once you have got it started choose the How does this work 
					section to find out about it.</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="What is this all about?">
			<p>Following a number of questions about the status of the antelope 
				sample application I thought I would make things a bit 
				clear.</p>
			<p>Firstly just to introduce myself - (Ben Gidley) - I work for a 
				company called Anite. Anite have been building web applications 
				using Turbine for a while and we like it a lot. </p>
			<p>In the last year we have been working on a major project 
				building an intranet application using Turbine. This project 
				was the largest turbine project and let us to expand the number 
				of developers working with Turbine significantly. </p>
			<p>During this process we realised that getting started with 
				Turbine (especially with the extra components we use) was very 
				hard. So we decided to write a sample application 
				(antelope).</p>
			<p>Another key component of our large application was a workflow 
				engine (Zebra) - this engine when used with Turbine gives a 
				very nice web development environment. We have decided to open 
				source Zebra (we are still in the process of extracting it 
				fully from commercial code) - this will reside on 
				zebra.berlios.de.</p>
			<p>The aim from Anite's point of view is to use Antelope as a 
				training application and a base for new projects based on 
				Zebra/Turbine. Currently antelope only has Turbine based 
				elements in - the really cool stuff is not there yet! Currently 
				we don't plan to move Zebra and Antelope to jakarta - as they 
				do not yet meet the criteria to be a project (as only Anite are 
				involved) - longer term we may consider this. We don't want to 
				split them up either as Antelope is designed to be a sample of 
				how to use Turbine with the Zebra engine as well as without 
				it.</p>
			<p>In short Antelope is a best practice sample of the 'Anite' way 
				of using Turbine. As Anite now have a large investment in both 
				current and older Turbine applications we intend to keep 
				Antelope up to date and current.</p>
			<p>On the subject of version of Turbine we are using a recent 
				Turbine CVS HEAD. My opinion is this is basically stable as far 
				as someone developing an application using Turbine is 
				concerned. The bits that are changing are in the guts of 
				turbine. We have successfully ported back and forth between 2.3 
				and 2.4 HEAD with almost no code changes. Obviously it would be 
				better to use a release version - but we wanted the pipeline 
				which is only in 2.4.</p>
			<p>On Flux vs Antelope - Antelope has a security manager because 
				Anite needed one and we thought why not put in antelope! It 
				uses Fulcrum security and I doubt Flux would work with Fulcrum 
				Security. Also (I didn't write it!) I think the GUI is better 
				than Flux's. </p>
			<p>We are very happy that people are using Antelope - and hope it 
				will become a great Turbine sample and help people get started. 
				</p>
			<p>A number of people who comment frequently on this list have been 
				working for Anite on Antelope and the other elements such as 
				Mike Jones (mainly antelope), Peter Courcoux (Turbine Review), 
				Eric Pugh (Antelope and Zebra), Matthew Norris (designer of 
				Zebra) and myself. </p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>